We're interested in more than that. We're interested in the climate. That's years, that's millennia, and we need to go to even smaller scales. The stuff that we can't resolve, the sub-scale processes, we need to approximate in some way. That is a huge challenge. Climate models in the 1990s took an even smaller chunk of that, only about three orders of magnitude. Climate models in the 2010s, kind of what we're working with now, four orders of magnitude. We have 14 to go, and we're increasing our capability of simulating those at about one extra order of magnitude every decade. One extra order of magnitude in space is 10,000 times more calculations. And we keep adding more things, more questions to these different models. So what does a climate model look like? This is an old climate model, admittedly, a punch card, a single line of Fortran code. We no longer use punch cards. We do still use Fortran. New-fangled ideas like C really haven't had a big impact on the climate modeling community. But how do we go about doing it? How do we go from that complexity that you saw to a line of code? We do it one piece at a time. This is a picture of sea ice taken flying over the Arctic. We can look at all of the different equations that go into making the ice grow or melt or change shape. We can look at the fluxes. We can look at the rate at which snow turns to ice, and we can code that. We can encapsulate that in code. These models are around a million lines of code at this point, and growing by tens of thousands of lines of code every year. So you can look at that piece, but you can look at the other pieces too. What happens when you have clouds? What happens when clouds form, when they dissipate, when they rain out? That's another piece. What happens when we have radiation coming from the sun, going through the atmosphere, being absorbed and reflected? We can code each of those very small pieces as well. There are other pieces: the winds changing the ocean currents. We can talk about the role of vegetation in transporting water from the soils back into the atmosphere. And each of these different elements we can encapsulate and put into a system. Each of those pieces ends up adding to the whole. And you get something like this. You get a beautiful representation of what's going on in the climate system, where each and every one of those emergent patterns that you can see, the swirls in the Southern Ocean, the tropical cyclone in the Gulf of Mexico, and there's two more that are going to pop up in the Pacific at any point now, those rivers of atmospheric water, all of those are emergent properties that come from the interactions of all of those small-scale processes I mentioned. There's no code that says, "Do a wiggle in the Southern Ocean." There's no code that says, "Have two tropical cyclones that spin around each other." All of those things are emergent properties. This is all very good. This is all great. But what we really want to know is what happens to these emergent properties when we kick the system? When something changes, what happens to those properties? And there's lots of different ways to kick the system. There are wobbles in the Earth's orbit over hundreds of thousands of years that change the climate. There are changes in the solar cycles, every 11 years and longer, that change the climate. Big volcanoes go off and change the climate. Changes in biomass burning, in smoke, in aerosol particles, all of those things change the climate. The ozone hole changed the climate. Deforestation changes the climate by changing the surface properties and how water is evaporated and moved around in the system. Contrails change the climate by creating clouds where there were none before, and of course greenhouse gases change the system. Each of these different kicks provides us with a target to evaluate whether we understand something about this system. So we can go to look at what model skill is. Now I use the word "skill" advisedly: Models are not right or wrong; they're always wrong. They're always approximations. The question you have to ask is whether a model tells you more information than you would have had otherwise. If it does, it's skillful. This is the impact of the ozone hole on sea level pressure, so low pressure, high pressures, around the southern oceans, around Antarctica. This is observed data. This is modeled data. There's a good match because we understand the physics that controls the temperatures in the stratosphere and what that does to the winds around the southern oceans. We can look at other examples. The eruption of Mount Pinatubo in 1991 put an enormous amount of aerosols, small particles, into the stratosphere. That changed the radiation balance of the whole planet. There was less energy coming in than there was before, so that cooled the planet, and those red lines and those green lines, those are the differences between what we expected and what actually happened. The models are skillful, not just in the global mean, but also in the regional patterns. I could go through a dozen more examples: the skill associated with solar cycles, changing the ozone in the stratosphere; the skill associated with orbital changes over 6,000 years. We can look at that too, and the models are skillful. The models are skillful in response to the ice sheets 20,000 years ago. The models are skillful when it comes to the 20th-century trends over the decades. Models are successful at modeling lake outbursts into the North Atlantic 8,000 years ago. And we can get a good match to the data. Each of these different targets, each of these different evaluations, leads us to add more scope to these models, and leads us to more and more complex situations that we can ask more and more interesting questions, like, how does dust from the Sahara, that you can see in the orange, interact with tropical cyclones in the Atlantic? How do organic aerosols from biomass burning, which you can see in the red dots, intersect with clouds and rainfall patterns? How does pollution, which you can see in the white wisps of sulfate pollution in Europe, how does that affect the temperatures at the surface and the sunlight that you get at the surface? We can look at this across the world. We can look at the pollution from China. We can look at the impacts of storms on sea salt particles in the atmosphere. We can see the combination of all of these different things happening all at once, and we can ask much more interesting questions. How do air pollution and climate coexist? Can we change things that affect air pollution and climate at the same time? The answer is yes. So this is a history of the 20th century. The first one is the model. The weather is a little bit different to what actually happened. The second one are the observations. And we're going through the 1930s. There's variability, there are things going on, but it's all kind of in the noise. As you get towards the 1970s, things are going to start to change. They're going to start to look more similar, and by the time you get to the 2000s, you're already seeing the patterns of global warming, both in the observations and in the model. We know what happened over the 20th century. Right? We know that it's gotten warmer. We know where it's gotten warmer. And if you ask the models why did that happen, and you say, okay, well, yes, basically it's because of the carbon dioxide we put into the atmosphere. We have a very good match up until the present day. But there's one key reason why we look at models, and that's because of this phrase here. Because if we had observations of the future, we obviously would trust them more than models, But unfortunately, observations of the future are not available at this time. So when we go out into the future, there's a difference. The future is unknown, the future is uncertain, and there are choices. Here are the choices that we have. We can do some work to mitigate the emissions of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere. That's the top one. We can do more work to really bring it down so that by the end of the century, it's not much more than there is now. Or we can just leave it to fate and continue on with a business-as-usual type of attitude. The differences between these choices can't be answered by looking at models. There's a great phrase that Sherwood Rowland, who won the Nobel Prize for the chemistry that led to ozone depletion, when he was accepting his Nobel Prize, he asked this question: "What is the use of having developed a science well enough to make predictions if, in the end, all we're willing to do is stand around and wait for them to come true?" The models are skillful, but what we do with the information from those models is totally up to you. Thank you. (Applause)
Nos interesa mucho más que eso. Nos interesa el clima. Esto es años, milenios, y necesitamos ir a escalas aún menores. A lo que no podemos resolver, los procesos de las subescalas, necesitamos aproximarnos de algún modo. Es un reto enorme. En la década de 1990, los modelos climatológicos tomaban un trozo aún más pequeño, de tan solo tres órdenes de magnitud, En la década actual, estamos trabajando con alrededor de 4 órdenes de magnitud. Nos faltan 14 y estamos aumentando nuestra capacidad de simularlos alrededor de un orden de magnitud por década. Un orden extra de magnitud en espacio equivale a 10 000 veces más cálculos. Y seguimos añadiendo más cosas, más preguntas a estos diversos modelos. ¿Cómo se ve un modelo climático? Este es un modelo climático antiguo, una tarjeta perforada, una línea de código Fortran. Ya no usamos tarjetas perforadas. Pero aún empleamos Fortran. Las ideas modernas como el lenguaje C no han tenido un gran impacto en la comunidad de modelado climático. Pero ¿cómo seguimos haciéndolo? ¿Cómo vamos de la complejidad que vieron a una línea de código? Lo hacemos uno por uno. Esta es una imagen de mar de hielo tomada en un sobrevuelo en el Ártico Podemos ver las distintas ecuaciones que describen el crecimiento de hielo o su derretimiento o cambio de forma. Podemos ver los flujos. Podemos ver el ritmo al que la nieve se convierte en hielo, y podemos codificarlo. Podemos encapsularlo en un código. Estos modelos son de cerca de un millón de líneas de código en este punto. y crecen unas decenas de miles de líneas de código cada año. Pueden ver esta pieza, pero también las demás piezas. ¿Qué pasa cuando hay nubes? ¿Qué pasa cuando las nubes se forman, se disipan, se precipitan? Es otra pieza. ¿Qué pasa cuando la radiación solar que penetra la atmósfera se absorbe y se refleja? Podemos codificar cada uno de ellos también en piezas muy pequeñas. Hay otras piezas: Los vientos que cambian las corrientes oceánicas. Podemos hablar del papel de la vegetación en el transporte del agua del suelo hacia la atmósfera. Y cada uno de esos diversos elementos pueden encapsularse y ponerse en un sistema. Cada una de esas partes termina por sumarse al conjunto. Y el resultado es similar a esto. Una hermosa representación de lo que sucede en el sistema climático, en el que cada uno de esos patrones emergentes que pueden ver, los remolinos en el Océano del sur, el ciclón tropical en el Golfo de México, y otros dos más por surgir en el Pacífico en cualquier momento, esos ríos de agua atmosférica, todos esos son propiedades emergentes que provienen de las interacciones de todos esos procesos a pequeña escala que mencioné. No hay un código que diga "Haga un giro en el océano del sur". "Haga dos ciclones que giren uno en torno del otro". Todas esas cosas son propiedades emergentes. Todo esto está muy bien. Es grandioso. Pero lo que queremos saber es ¿qué pasa con todas esas propiedades emergentes cuando pateamos el sistema? ¿Qué pasa con esas propiedades cuando algo cambia? Y hay muchas maneras distintas de patear el sistema. Hay tambaleos en la órbita terrestre a lo largo de cientos de millones de años que alteran el clima. Hay cambios en los ciclos solares, cada 11 años aproximadamente, que cambian el clima Grandes volcanes se apagan y cambian el clima. Cambios en la quema de biomasa, humo, partículas en aerosol y todas esas cosas alteran el clima. El hoyo en la capa de ozono alteró el clima. La deforestación cambia el clima al cambiar las propiedades de la superficie y en cómo se evapora del agua y en cómo se mueve en el sistema. Las estelas de condensación alteran el clima al crear nubes en donde no había y, desde luego, los gases de efecto invernadero alteran el sistema. Cada uno de esos factores nos da una oportunidad para evaluar si entendemos algo de este sistema. Podemos ver qué tan preciso es el modelo. Hablo de "precisión" intencionalmente: Los modelos no están bien o mal: siempre están mal. Siempre son aproximaciones. La pregunta que hay que hacerse es si un modelo da más información que algún otro. Si es así, es preciso. Este es el impacto del agujero en la capa de ozono en la presión a nivel de mar, baja presión, alta presión, alrededor de los mares del sur, alrededor de la Antártica. Este es el dato observado. Este es el modelo del dato. Hay una buena similitud porque entendemos la física que controla las temperaturas en la estratósfera y lo que hacen los vientos alrededor de los mares del sur. Podemos ver otros ejemplos. La erupción del volcán Pinatubo en 1991 dejó una enorme cantidad de aerosoles, pequeñas partículas, en la estratósfera. Eso cambió el balance de radiación en el planeta entero. Había menos energía llegando que antes, así que la Tierra se enfrió y esas líneas rojas y esas líneas verdes son la diferencia entre lo que se esperaba y lo que en realidad pasó. Los modelos son precisos, no solo a escala global, sino en patrones locales. Podría poner una docena más de ejemplos: la precisión asociada con los ciclos solares que cambia el ozono en la estratósfera; la precisión asociada con los cambios en la órbita durante 6000 años. Podemos estudiarlos y los modelos son precisos. Los modelos son precisos de acuerdo a las capas de hielo de hace 20 000 años. Los modelos son precisos cuando se buscan tendencias en el siglo XX entre décadas. Los modelos son exitosos para modelar surgimientos de lagos en el Atlántico norte hace 8 000 años. Y podemos tener una buena aproximación a los datos. Cada uno de estos diferentes objetivos, cada uno de las diferentes evaluaciones, nos lleva a agregar mayor alcance a estos modelos, y nos lleva a situaciones más y más complejas en las que podemos hacer preguntas más y más interesantes, como, ¿cómo el polvo del Sahara, que pueden ver es naranja, interactúa con los ciclones tropicales en el atlántico? ¿Cómo el aerosol orgánico de la quema de biomasa, que pueden ver en puntos rojos, interactúa con los patrones de nubes y lluvias? ¿Cómo la contaminación, que pueden ver en los remolinos blancos de contaminación por sulfatos en Europa, afecta la temperatura en la superficie y en la luz solar que llega a la superficie? Podemos ver esto en todo el mundo. Podemos ver la contaminación de China. Podemos ver el impacto de las tormentas sobre las partículas de sal de mar en la atmósfera. Podemos ver la combinación de todas esas distintas cosas ocurriendo al mismo tiempo y podemos hacernos preguntas aún más interesantes. ¿Cómo coexisten la contaminación atmosférica y el clima? ¿Podemos cambiar elementos que afectan tanto la contaminación como el clima? La respuesta es sí. Así que esta la historia del siglo XX. El primero es el modelo. El clima es un poco diferente de lo que en realidad pasó. La segunda son las observaciones. Y vamos por la década de los treinta. Hay cambios, están pasando cosas, pero es como una especie ruido. Mientras nos acercamos a la década de los setenta las cosas empiezan a cambiar. Empiezan a verse más similares, y para el siglo XXI ya estamos viendo el patrón del calentamiento global, tanto en las observaciones como en el modelo. Sabemos qué ocurrió en el siglo XX. Sabemos que se hizo más cálido. Sabemos dónde se hizo más cálido. Y si le preguntan a los modelos por qué ocurrió y dicen, bueno, bien, sí, básicamente por el dióxido de carbono que pusimos en la atmósfera. Tenemos un buen ajuste hasta el día de hoy. Pero hay una razón fundamental de por qué recurrimos a los modelos y es por esta frase. Porque si tuviéramos mediciones del futuro obviamente confiaríamos más en ellas que en los modelos, pero desgraciadamente, las mediciones del futuro todavía no están disponibles. Así que cuando llegamos al futuro, hay diferencias. El futuro es desconocido, es incierto y hay alternativas. Estas son las alternativas que tenemos. Podemos hacer algo para mitigar las emisiones de dióxido de carbono en la atmósfera. Esa es la primera. Podemos trabajar para realmente bajarlos para que al fin de siglo, no sea mucho más de lo que hay ahora. O lo dejamos a su suerte y seguimos con nuestra actitud de "no pasa nada". La diferencia entre esas alternativas se puede ver en los modelos. Hay una gran cita de Sherwood Rowland, que ganó el Premio Nobel de Química por estudiar el agotamiento del ozono, cuando estaba aceptando el premio Nobel preguntó lo siguiente: ¿Cuál es el fin de desarrollar una ciencia capaz de hacer predicciones, si al final todos nos quedamos quietos esperando a que se hagan realidad? Los modelos son precisos, pero lo que hagamos con la información de esos modelos está en nuestras manos. Gracias. (Aplausos)